<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="faq">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
  <para>
    Please read through these common questions and answers before asking
    developers.
  </para>

  <sect1 id="faq-sessionpolicy">
    <title>
      How does OHM fit in with other session policy agents?
    </title>
    <para>
      At the moment, no distributions ship OHM, so there is no problem.
      When they do, session power daemons will talk to <literal>hald</literal>
      and <literal>ohmd</literal> together, and there should be no visible
      changes to the user.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-specificdevice">
    <title>
      Why not just do a specific device hack for all the different
      embedded hardware?
    </title>
    <para>
      As lots of manufacturers are hacking the same thing, over and over.
      We need some sort of central common framework.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-lgpl">
    <title>
      So it's LGPL... does that mean some of the code is closed source?
    </title>
    <para>
      No. It just means that code protected by intellectual property laws
      can be used by manufacturers, but OHM works really well without any
      non-free stuff.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-installcode">
    <title>
      Can I install the latest stable code?
    </title>
    <para>
      No, at the moment it is proof of concept and only really useful for
      developers. Feel free to look at the code and spec and give feedback,
      but please don't expect anything to actually work well yet.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-releasedate">
    <title>
      What is the release date plan for OHM?
    </title>
    <para>
      Currently we are aiming at a 2 month stakeholder involvement prototype
      period, and then 10 months of code polishing and maturing.
      That gives an approximate release date of January 2008
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-systemprefs">
    <title>
      Do you need to use system GConf for the system preferences?
    </title>
    <para>
      No. We plan to use a flat file for minimum dependencies and speed,
      and also each file is going to be really small and simple.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-noxml">
    <title>
      Is OHM using XML to define the policy rules?
    </title>
    <para>
      No, as we don't need to.
      We are using compiled logic for speed and low dependencies.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-whysessionlayer">
    <title>
      Why include a session layer for embedded appliances?
    </title>
    <para>
      Devices can omit the session layer, and talk directly to OHM on the
      system bus. This removes the ability to do fast user switching or
      have multiple logged in users and does reduce security.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-whysinglehash">
    <title>
      Why are all the keys exposed in a single hash table?
    </title>
    <para>
      Plugins have to query to state of other plugins.
      To store the state of each plugin in itself, we would have to do
      inter-plugin methods, and expose the SetKey and GetKey methods on every
      plugin.
      We can also optimise the global keystore for a fast hash lookup to avoid
      scalability problems.
      This also makes it easier to code as the keystore can just be a
      compiled <literal>.o</literal> object rather than a shared library.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="faq-restartdeps">
    <title>
      Will OHM break if I restart <literal>messagebus</literal> or
      <literal>hald</literal>?
    </title>
    <para>
      Yes. Please restart your computer if you want to restart these daemons.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
