<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Open Hardware Manager Introduction</title>

  <sect1 id="introduction-description">
    <title>Overall Description</title>

    <para>
      OHM is a small open source systems daemon which sits above HAL and
      abstracts out common hardware management tasks such as:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          System wide power management statistics (for instance calculating
          hysteresis of battery curves).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Managing system wide inhibit actions, for instance system
          firmware updating.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Controlling heat dissipation on embedded and PC devices.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      OHM is built using a plugin architecture with a low-overhead messaging
      structure.
      This gives a very configurable base system that can be configured in many
      different ways.
      Each plugin can query data from HAL or execute methods on HAL devices and
      expose preferences interfaces for session-space to use.
    </para>

    <mediaobject id="ohm-structure">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="ohm-structure.png" align="center"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
 
    <para>
      OHM is LGPL licensed to allow proprietary licensed plug-ins to be used
      where absolutely required.
      It is also uses the minimum of memory and processor requirement to fulfill
      the task.
      This makes it suitable for use on the latest smart-phones, the OLPC device
      or any other embedded products such as set top boxes.
    </para>

    <para>
      HAL has traditionally been seen too heavyweight for use on an embedded device.
      While this was once true, there have been very many developers working on
      adding conditional compilation to parts of HAL, and to reduce memory usage.
      This can be seen with the startup speed of 0.5.9 being 40% than of 0.5.8.
      Context switching has been reduced, and memory pressure on coldplug has been
      reduced for devices with a small amount of devices.
      It is expected that <literal>hald</literal> will start in the few hundred
      millisecond range and consume less than half a megabyte of RAM at coldplug.
    </para>

    <para>
      Using HAL allows us to use a common framework for hardware management,
      which means plugins designed for one architecture or chip will work on
      any other system.
      Working together is the best way to get high quality, maintainable code
      rather than all the hacky systems we have now.
    </para>

    <mediaobject id="ohm-sessions">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="ohm-sessions.png" align="center"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>
      Proof of concept code is available on the project page.
      There are no tarball releases yet, checking out using git is the best
      option.
    </para>

    <para>
      OHM comprises:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <literal>ohmd</literal> system daemon which co-ordinates the
          rules and acts as a keystore for multiple users.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The interface specification which outlines core
          <literal>ohmd</literal> functionality
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A method for plugins to request notification when keys change, for
          example when the system AC state is changed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
           The test suite which tests functionality
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      OHM is very suitable for embedded devices that need to manage power, heat
      and other critical tasks early in the boot sequence.
      Using HAL, it provides an abstract method for all plugins to be written in
      a generic way, not tied to the specific implementation of the device.
    </para>

    <para>
      What OHM is not:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A power saving daemon.
          It is not doing power saving specifically, it is just doing device
          specific rules that manage power and heat dissipation and other
          hardware specific stuff.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An abstraction of HAL. HAL acts as the input and the output of OHM,
          and OHM enforces policy for HAL.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A huge daemon with lots of dependencies.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          API or ABI stable. Expect the ABI and API to change on a regular
          basis until we ship 1.0.0.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Targeted to a particular architecture or platform.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Produced by any one vendor.
          There are many contributors helping to get this done.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Why not do everything in a session daemon?:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Sometimes we need to start very early in the boot sequence.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We don't want to die if X dies.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          On a server with 100 logged in users we don't want an instance for
          each user.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          We need to apply policy at boot-up or before X starts.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="introduction-plugins">
    <title>Plugins</title>
    <para>
      Plugins have keys and policy, and also install a default system
      preferences file.
    </para>

    <para>
      We need to set system preferences when there is no user logged in or we
      are very early in the boot sequence.
      We do this with each plugin installing a text file with the plugin key
      name, the value, and optionally the public switch.
    </para>

    <para>
      The core setup file is read from <filename>/etc/ohm/core</filename> and
      plugin preferences are read from <filename>/etc/ohm/plugins/{name}</filename>
      Comments are lines with first character <literal>#</literal> and then the
      rest of the line is ignored.
      Files are flat text with the following formal description, 
      <literal>plugin_prefix.key value type public</literal>
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        There is a single space between the values.
        Line endings have to be UNIX not WIN or MAC.
        Parsing is very strict, and <literal>ohmd</literal> will exit with an
        error if the syntax is not perfect. This is by design.
      </para>
    </important>

    <note>
      <para>
        Public is only set if the key can be changed by the session, and if the
        key is tried to be set, the set method will fail.
        This is a way to enforce fine-grained rules on users when writing
        PolicyKit rules for every action would be too great an overhead.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>
      Plugins can tell <literal>ohmd</literal> that other plugins are required
      for certain functionality, for instance, the backlight unit on a mobile
      phone may require the temperature module to be present, so it can do the
      temperature shutdown checks.
      This is done with <literal>ohm_module_require()</literal>.
      <literal>ohmd</literal> daemon will fail to load if any required plugin
      is not present after the plugins have finished initializing.
    </para>

    <para>
      Plugins can also tell <literal>ohmd</literal> that other plugins are suggested for certain
      functionality, for instance, the backlight unit may work best when the
      battery plugin is loaded so we can dim when we are low on power.
      This is done with <literal>ohm_module_suggest()</literal>.
      <literal>ohmd</literal> daemon will print a message to the console if any
      suggested plugin is not present.
    </para>

    <para>
      Plugins can also tell <literal>ohmd</literal> that other plugins are banned, for instance,
      a proprietary battery discharge plugin maybe incompatible with the
      standard battery plugin.
      This is done with <literal>ohm_module_prevent()</literal>.
      <literal>ohmd</literal> will fail to load if any prevented plugin is
      manually loaded or loaded through a dependency of another plugin.
    </para>

    <para>
      In <literal>ohmd</literal>, keys are created read/write by the plugin.
      Other plugins can watch for changes on these keys (even on other modules)
      using <literal>ohm_key_monitor()</literal>.
      The callback will be issued local to the plugin when the state of this
      key changes.
    </para>

    <para>
      NOTE: There is no ordering of priority (yet?) of monitored keys.
      Make sure that policy per key is kept to one plugin, else strange
      races might start happening.
    </para>

    <para>
      A library called <literal>libohm</literal> allows system and session
      programs to easily interface with <literal>ohmd</literal>.
      This library will remove the implementation detail from plugins and
      session applications.
      This library, like the rest of OHM will not be API or ABI stable until
      version 1.0.0 is released.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="introduction-deps">
    <title>Dependencies</title>
    <para>
      OHM is lightweight.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          GLib 2.10.0 (required)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          DBUS 0.70 (required)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          HAL 0.5.8 (required)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          PolicyKit (optional)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          ConsoleKit (optional)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
